Sailavanya Narthu

sailavanyanarthu0710@gmail.com | +1 (312)-647-0895 | Seattle, Washington | https://sailavanya1.github.io/https://www.linkedin.com/in/sailavanya-narthu/ | https://github.com/SaiLavanya1?tab=repositories

SUMMARY

Software Developer/Engineer with 1.5 years of experience in Java and Python, a strong passion for Machine Learning, and proven problem-solving abilities. Eager to contribute to groundbreaking projects while honing skills in software engineering and machine learning domains.

EDUCATION

Illinois Institute of Technology - Master's in Computer Science

Software Engineering, Big Data Technologies, Advanced Database, Machine Learning

ANITS - Bachelor of Technology in Information Technology

Data Structures, Artificial Intelligence, Operating Systems, Distributed Systems, Computer Networks

Aug 2022 - May 2024 Chicago, Illinois Jun 2017 - May 2021

Vizag, India

TECHNICAL SKILLS and CERTIFICATIONS

- Programming: Java, Python, JavaScript, C, C++, C#, SQL, R
- Web Technologies: HTML, CSS, ReactJs, JQuery, SpringBoot, NodeJs, Bootstrap, Angular, Django, MERN Stack
- Databases/BigData: MYSQL, PLSQL, MongoDB, DocumentDB, Google Cloud, CI/CD pipelines, Hadoop, Hive, Kafka
- Other Technologies: Microservices, RESTful APIs, AWS, Azure, Git, Jira, Agile, SDLC, Docker, Numpy, Pandas, TensorFlow
- **Certifications:** Azure Fundamentals(AZ 900), AWS Certification Course(Udemy)

WORK EXPERIENCE

One Community Global, Seattle, Washington

July 2024 - Present

- Software Engineer , Remote
 - Developed and hosted **MERN stack** applications, integrating **MongoDB**, Express.js middleware, Node.js, and Java components for the Highest Good Network (HGN) **React** application, impacting over 10,000 users.
 - Implemented new features, managed development and production environments, and adhered to coding standards and best practices.
 - Managed the full software development lifecycle, version control with GitHub, and cloud deployments with Microsoft Azure.
 - Collaborated with global teams of 100+ developers using Agile methodologies and Slack, contributing to automated testing, documentation, and open-source projects, ensuring high-quality software delivery and impactful improvements.

Tata Consultancy Services, Hyderabad, India

Software Developer [Tech: Java, Spring Framework, JavaScript, RESTful APIs, Kafka and SQL]

July 2021 – July 2022

- Developed and maintained scalable, cloud-ready software applications for Bank of America, optimizing transaction processing, customer account management, and risk assessment functionalities.
- Utilized Java, Spring Boot, JavaScript, and SQL to design and implement solutions, adhering to coding standards, best practices, and distributed system principles that are foundational for cloud platforms like **Microsoft Azure**.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to gather requirements and translate into technical specifications, driving project success.
- Conducted comprehensive code reviews, identifying areas for improvement and implementing changes to enhance performance and maintainability.
- Enhanced customer retention by 15% and increased upselling revenue by 10% through addressing client requests promptly.

Hebeon Technologies Hyderabad, India

Python Developer Intern [Tech: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Scikit-learn, Git]

Jul 2020 – Aug 2020

- Constructed a machine learning model using **Python** and advanced regression algorithms (Linear Regression, Decision Trees, Random Forests) to predict employee salaries based on experience levels.
- Demonstrated the ability to bridge gaps between data science and business objectives through successful model implementation with an accuracy of 92%.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Amazon Clone — https:/github.com/SaiLavanya1/Amazon-Clone

Jan 2024

- Developed a high-fidelity Amazon Clone using JavaScript, React, Firebase, HTML/CSS, and NodeJs. Integrated key features such as user authentication, real-time database, and serverless functions.
- Demonstrated proficiency in full-stack development and rapid prototyping. Leveraged React Context API for efficient state
 management, slashing error rates and processing time by 50%.

Traffic Flow Analysis in Different Weather Conditions — https://github.com/SaiLavanya1/ML_PROJECT

Nov 2022

- Analyzed and forecasted traffic patterns with Python, GIS, Numpy, Pandas, and Matplotlib, leveraging **AWS services** such as Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud (EC2) for processing large volumes of traffic data.
- Processed sensor data and accounted for various weather conditions to simulate real-time data processing challenges, achieving an accuracy of 90%.

Image Detection of roads using computer vision — https://qithub.com/SaiLavanya1/Project-BTech

May 2021

- Implemented a robust image classifier with Python, TensorFlow, CNN, OpenCV, Tableau and Edge Detection to identify
 accidents in self-driving car scenarios.
- This project highlights expertise in computer vision techniques relevant to the field of machine learning, ultimately
 contributing to the development of safer autonomous vehicle systems.